<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>urn:2024-10-13T01:12:57.824Z</id>
    <title>osmos::feed</title>
    <updated>2024-10-13T01:12:57.824Z</updated>
    <generator>osmosfeed 1.15.1</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="index.html"/>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[From software to reality?]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21713</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/10/09/from-software-to-reality/"/>
        <updated>2024-10-09T13:21:37.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Both the Physics and Chemistry Nobel prizes were awarded to computer scientists in 2024. Computer scientists are emerging as leading figures in the natural sciences. In turn, these sciences are increasingly dominated by theorists and modelers. There has a noticeable shift in some scientific fields where theoretical models and simulations often not only precede experimental … Continue reading From software to reality?]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Netflix’s TimeSeries Data Abstraction Layer]]></title>
        <id>https://medium.com/p/31552f6326f8</id>
        <link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/introducing-netflix-timeseries-data-abstraction-layer-31552f6326f8?source=rss----2615bd06b42e---4"/>
        <updated>2024-10-08T17:05:36.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Rajiv Shringi, Vinay Chella, Kaidan Fullerton, Oleksii Tkachuk, Joey Lynch]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Netflix Technology Blog</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Geoffrey Hinton, the Godfather of Deep Learning, wins Nobel Prize in Physics!]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21710</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/10/08/geoffrey-hinton-the-godfather-of-deep-learning-wins-nobel-prize-in-physics/"/>
        <updated>2024-10-08T13:29:44.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[So… in 2024, the Physics Nobel prize was awarded to a Computer Scientist. Is Physics out of ideas? The Nobel Committee just gave a Physics award to a COMPUTER SCIENTIST! What does this say about the state of modern Physics?  Though the first half of the XXth century was filled with breakthrough in Physics, it … Continue reading Geoffrey Hinton, the Godfather of Deep Learning, wins Nobel Prize in Physics!]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Two Workflow Tips]]></title>
        <id>https://matklad.github.io/2024/10/08/two-tips.html</id>
        <link href="https://matklad.github.io/2024/10/08/two-tips.html"/>
        <updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[An article about a couple of relatively recent additions to my workflow which I wish I knew about
years ago.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>matklad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Windows dynamic linking depends on the active code page]]></title>
        <id>https://nullprogram.com/blog/2024/10/07/</id>
        <link href="https://nullprogram.com/blog/2024/10/07/"/>
        <updated>2024-10-07T19:50:17.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Windows paths have been WTF-16-encoded for decades, but module names
in the import tables of Portable Executable are octets.
If a name contains values beyond ASCII — technically out of spec — then
the dynamic linker must somehow decode those octets into Unicode in order
to construct a lookup path. There are multiple ways this could be done,
and the most obvious is the process’s active code page (ACP), which is
exactly what happens. As a consequence, the specific DLL loaded by the
linker may depend on the system code page. In this article I’ll contrive
such a situation.
LoadLibraryA is a similar situation, and potentially applies the code
page to a longer portion of the module path. LoadLibraryW is
unaffected, at least for the directly-named module, because it’s Unicode
all the way through.…]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>null program</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iterating through matched characters in modern C++]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21702</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/10/06/iterating-through-matched-characters-in-modern-c-viewsfilter-and-coroutine/"/>
        <updated>2024-10-06T21:52:13.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Consider the following problem. You want to iterate through the characters of a strings and find only those matching some criteria. For example, you might want scan an HTML string looking for the characters ‘<‘, ‘&’, ‘\0’, ‘\n’. We might do it in C++ using the find_first_of function. It is a generic function that is … Continue reading Iterating through matched characters in modern C++]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Ousterhout's Dichotomy]]></title>
        <id>https://matklad.github.io/2024/10/06/ousterhouts-dichotomy.html</id>
        <link href="https://matklad.github.io/2024/10/06/ousterhouts-dichotomy.html"/>
        <updated>2024-10-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why are there so many programming languages? One of the driving reasons for this is that some
languages tend to produce fast code, but are a bit of a pain to use (C++), while others are a breeze
to write, but run somewhat slow (Python). Depending on the ratio of CPUs to programmers, one or the
other might be relatively more important.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>matklad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Slim Reader/Writer Locks are neato]]></title>
        <id>https://nullprogram.com/blog/2024/10/03/</id>
        <link href="https://nullprogram.com/blog/2024/10/03/"/>
        <updated>2024-10-03T22:40:13.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m 18 years late, but Slim Reader/Writer Locks have a fantastic
interface: pointer-sized (“slim”), zero-initialized, and non-allocating.
Lacking cleanup, they compose naturally with arena allocation.
Sounds like a futex? That’s because they’re built on futexes introduced at
the same time. They’re also complemented by condition variables
with the same desirable properties. My only quibble is that slim locks
could easily have been 32-bit objects, but it hardly matters. This
article, while treating Win32 as a foreign interface, discusses a
paper-thin C++ wrapper interface around lock and condition variables, in
my own style.
If you’d like to see/try a complete, working demonstration before diving
into the details: demo.cpp. We’re going to build this from the
ground up, so let’s establish a f…]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>null program</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nim versions 2.2.0 and 2.0.10 released]]></title>
        <id>https://nim-lang.org//blog/2024/10/02/nim-220-2010.html</id>
        <link href="https://nim-lang.org//blog/2024/10/02/nim-220-2010.html"/>
        <updated>2024-10-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Nim Team is happy to announce two releases:
version 2.2.0, our new stable release
version 2.0.10, a patch release for Nim 2.0
Nim v2.2.0 is a continuation of our efforts to improve Nim 2: it contains almost 1000 new commits, bringing improvements to the ORC memory management and to the language and the compiler overall.
Nim v2.0.10 is a patch release aimed at our enterprise users who cannot immediately switch to Nim 2.2, containing 80 commits with bugfixes.
Nim 2.2.0
Release highlights
Many long-standing compiler bugs with generics, typedesc and static types have been fixed in this release, effectively making these features stable.
In particular, arbitrary expressions for types and values in generic types are now largely functional when they only worked in specific cases before.
The re…]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Nim Programming Language</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[It is never too late to write your own C/C++ command-line utilities]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21694</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/09/28/it-is-never-too-later-to-write-your-own-c-c-command-line-utilities/"/>
        <updated>2024-09-28T04:06:18.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently, I received an email from an engineer at a prominent company who shared how he managed to save his employer tens of thousands of dollars annually by developing a custom command-line utility in C++. Without delving into specifics (which remain confidential), the company’s servers were tasked with querying a JSON file for a specific … Continue reading It is never too late to write your own C/C++ command-line utilities]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Watermelon Operator]]></title>
        <id>https://matklad.github.io/2024/09/24/watermelon-operator.html</id>
        <link href="https://matklad.github.io/2024/09/24/watermelon-operator.html"/>
        <updated>2024-09-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In these two most excellent articles,
https://without.boats/blog/let-futures-be-futures
and
https://without.boats/blog/futures-unordered, 
withoutboats introduces the concepts of multi-task and intra-task concurrency.
I want to revisit this distinction --- while I agree that there are different classes
of patterns of concurrency here, I am not quite satisfied with this specific partitioning of the
design space. I will use Rust-like syntax for most of the examples, but I am more interested in the
language-agnostic patterns, rather than in Rust's specific implementation of async.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>matklad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is io_uring?]]></title>
        <id>https://matklad.github.io/2024/09/23/what-is-io-uring.html</id>
        <link href="https://matklad.github.io/2024/09/23/what-is-io-uring.html"/>
        <updated>2024-09-23T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[An attempt at concise explanation of what io_uring is.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>matklad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Netflix’s Key-Value Data Abstraction Layer]]></title>
        <id>https://medium.com/p/1ea8a0a11b30</id>
        <link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/introducing-netflixs-key-value-data-abstraction-layer-1ea8a0a11b30?source=rss----2615bd06b42e---4"/>
        <updated>2024-09-18T22:49:04.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Vidhya Arvind, Rajasekhar Ummadisetty, Joey Lynch, Vinay Chella]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Netflix Technology Blog</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>