<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>urn:2023-07-09T01:19:22.733Z</id>
    <title>osmos::feed</title>
    <updated>2023-07-09T01:19:22.733Z</updated>
    <generator>osmosfeed 1.15.1</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="index.html"/>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stealth, not secrecy]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20671</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/07/08/stealth-not-secrecy/"/>
        <updated>2023-07-08T16:43:46.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The strategy for winning is simple: do good work and tell the world about it. In that order! This implies some level of stealth as you are doing the good work. If you plan to lose weight, don’t announce it… lose the weight and then do the reveal. Early feedback frames the problem and might … Continue reading Stealth, not secrecy]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Packing a string of digits into an integer quickly]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20663</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/07/07/packing-a-string-of-digits-into-an-integer-quickly/"/>
        <updated>2023-07-07T17:19:34.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Suppose that I give you a short string of digits, containing possibly spaces or other characters (e.g., "20141103 012910"). We would like to pack the digits into an integer (e.g., 0x20141103012910) so that the lexicographical order over the string matches the ordering of the integers. We can use the fact that in ASCII, the digits … Continue reading Packing a string of digits into an integer quickly]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jersey City]]></title>
        <id>https://thenumb.at/Jersey-City/</id>
        <link href="https://thenumb.at/Jersey-City/"/>
        <updated>2023-07-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jersey City, NJ, 2023]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Max Slater</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Having fun with string literal suffixes in C++]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20659</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/07/05/having-fun-with-string-literal-suffixes-in-c/"/>
        <updated>2023-07-05T21:38:25.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The C++11 standard introduced user-defined string suffixes. It also added regular  expressions to the C++ language as a standard feature. I wanted to have fun and see whether we could combine these features. Regular expressions are useful to check whether a given string matches a pattern. For example, the expression \d+ checks that the string … Continue reading Having fun with string literal suffixes in C++]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Parsing time stamps faster with SIMD instructions]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20651</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/07/01/parsing-time-stamps-faster-with-simd-instructions/"/>
        <updated>2023-07-01T21:38:06.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In software, it is common to represent time as a time-stamp string. It is usually specified by a time format string. Some standards use the format %Y%m%d%H%M%S meaning that we print the year, the month, the day, the hours, the minutes and the seconds. The current time as I write this blog post would be … Continue reading Parsing time stamps faster with SIMD instructions]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Computing] The problem with federated web apps]]></title>
        <id>https://www.devever.net/~hl/webappcoupling</id>
        <link href="https://www.devever.net/~hl/webappcoupling"/>
        <updated>2023-07-01T12:05:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trying to make web applications federated is a popular effort. Examples include
things like the “fediverse”, as well as various other efforts, like attempts to
make distributed software forges, and so on. However, all of these efforts
suffer from a problem which is fundamental in building federated applications
built on top of the web platform.</p></div></div>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>devever.net/~hl</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dynamic bit shuffle using AVX-512]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20642</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/06/29/dynamic-bit-shuffle-using-avx-512/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-29T15:59:01.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Suppose that you want to reorder, arbitrarily, the bits in a 64-bit word. This question was raised on Twitter by @experquisite. Formally, you might want to provide, for each of the 64 bit position, an original bit position you want to copy. Hence, the following code would reverse the bit order in your 64-bit word: … Continue reading Dynamic bit shuffle using AVX-512]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Version 1.6.14 released]]></title>
        <id>https://nim-lang.org//blog/2023/06/27/version-1614-released.html</id>
        <link href="https://nim-lang.org//blog/2023/06/27/version-1614-released.html"/>
        <updated>2023-06-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Nim team is happy to announce version 1.6.14, our seventh (and largest) patch release for
Nim 1.6.
Version 1.6.14 is a result of three months of hard work, and it contains
179 commits,
bringing lots of general improvements over 1.6.12.
This release contains more than the usual amount of commits for a patch release
because we want to give you the best Nim v1 experience, in case you won’t be able to
immediately switch to Nim v2, which will be our next release.
We would recommend to all of our users to upgrade and use version 1.6.14.
Installing Nim 1.6
New users
Check out if the package manager of your OS already ships version 1.6.14 or
install it as described here.
Existing users
If you have installed a previous version of Nim using choosenim,
getting Nim 1.6.14 is as easy as:
$ chooseni…]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Nim Programming Language</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solving "Two Sum" in C with a tiny hash table]]></title>
        <id>https://nullprogram.com/blog/2023/06/26/</id>
        <link href="https://nullprogram.com/blog/2023/06/26/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-26T19:38:18.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I came across a question: How does one efficiently solve Two Sum in C?
There’s a naive quadratic time solution, but also an amortized linear time
solution using a hash table. Without a built-in or standard library hash
table, the latter sounds onerous. However, a mask-step-index table,
a hash table construction suitable for many problems, requires only a few
lines of code. This approach is useful even when a standard hash table is
available, because by exploiting the known problem constraints, it
beats typical generic hash table performance by 1–2 orders of magnitude
(demo).
The Two Sum exercise, restated:
Given an integer array and target, return the distinct indices of two
elements that sum to the target.
In particular, the solution doesn’t find elements, but their indices. The
exercise …]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>null program</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science and Technology links (June 25 2023)]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20640</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/06/25/science-and-technology-links-june-25-2023/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-25T17:32:56.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Women in highly religious relationships report the highest levels of relationship quality. US politics is largely divided into two parties (Republicans and Democrats). People who are affiliated with the Republicans have many more kids. The Antartic ice shelves gained 661 gigaton of ice over the past decade. A low protein diet increases mortality among older … Continue reading Science and Technology links (June 25 2023)]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Hμblog] I don't trust Signal]]></title>
        <id>https://www.devever.net/~hl/u/202306#25a</id>
        <link href="https://www.devever.net/~hl/u/202306#25a"/>
        <updated>2023-06-25T10:34:12.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><ul><li><a href="https://blog.dijit.sh/i-don-t-trust-signal">I don't trust Signal</a></li></ul><p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Re: my article , this is another good article focused on Signal specifically and why it should not be considered trustworthy or secure.<a href="https://www.devever.net/~hl/webcrypto">Web-based cryptography is always snake oil</a></p></div></div>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>devever.net/~hl</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[[Computing] Web-based cryptography is always snake oil]]></title>
        <id>https://www.devever.net/~hl/webcrypto</id>
        <link href="https://www.devever.net/~hl/webcrypto"/>
        <updated>2023-06-25T08:38:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<div type="xhtml"><div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nowadays, there is an epidemic of web applications purporting to offer
“end-to-end” encryption. Examples might range from a file upload service,
which allows you to upload and share files of arbitrary size and promises
“end-to-end encryption”; or a web-based password safe service which claims that
it can't see your passwords because they're encrypted; or a web-based
cryptocurrency wallet.</p></div></div>]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>devever.net/~hl</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[My ranking of every Shakespeare play]]></title>
        <id>https://nullprogram.com/blog/2023/06/22/</id>
        <link href="https://nullprogram.com/blog/2023/06/22/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-22T19:10:25.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article was discussed on Hacker News.
A few years ago I set out on a personal journey to study and watch a
performance of each of Shakespeare’s 37 plays. I’ve reached my goal and,
though it’s not a usual topic around here, I wanted to get my thoughts
down while fresh. I absolutely loved some of these plays and performances,
and so I’d like to highlight them, especially because my favorites are,
with one exception, not “popular” plays. Per tradition, I begin with my
least enjoyed plays and work my way up. All performances were either a
recording of a live stage or an adaptation, so they’re also available to
you if you’re interested, though in most cases not for free. I’ll mention
notable performances when applicable. The availability of a great
performance certainly influenced my play …]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>null program</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Detecting Scene Changes in Audiovisual Content]]></title>
        <id>https://medium.com/p/77a61d3eaad6</id>
        <link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/detecting-scene-changes-in-audiovisual-content-77a61d3eaad6?source=rss----2615bd06b42e---4"/>
        <updated>2023-06-20T16:51:36.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Avneesh Saluja, Andy Yao, Hossein Taghavi]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Netflix Technology Blog</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[GitHub Merge Queue]]></title>
        <id>https://matklad.github.io/2023/06/18/GitHub-merge-queue.html</id>
        <link href="https://matklad.github.io/2023/06/18/GitHub-merge-queue.html"/>
        <updated>2023-06-18T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Short, unedited note on GitHub merge queue.]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>matklad</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating Netflix to GraphQL Safely]]></title>
        <id>https://medium.com/p/8e1e4d4f1e72</id>
        <link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/migrating-netflix-to-graphql-safely-8e1e4d4f1e72?source=rss----2615bd06b42e---4"/>
        <updated>2023-06-14T17:59:46.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[By Jennifer Shin, Tejas Shikhare, Will Emmanuel]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Netflix Technology Blog</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Citogenesis in science and the importance of real problems]]></title>
        <id>http://lemire.me/blog/?p=3931</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/06/14/citogenesis-in-science-and-the-importance-of-real-problems/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-14T10:05:44.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Scientists publish papers in refereed journals and conferences: they write up their results and we ask anonymous referees to assess it. If the work is published, presumably because the anonymous referees found nothing objectionable, the published paper joins the “literature”. It is not a strict requirement: you can do excellent research without publishing in refereed … Continue reading Citogenesis in science and the importance of real problems]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Migrating Critical Traffic At Scale with No Downtime — Part 2]]></title>
        <id>https://medium.com/p/4b1c8c7155c1</id>
        <link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/migrating-critical-traffic-at-scale-with-no-downtime-part-2-4b1c8c7155c1?source=rss----2615bd06b42e---4"/>
        <updated>2023-06-13T17:23:17.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Shyam Gala, Javier Fernandez-Ivern, Anup Rokkam Pratap, Devang Shah]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Netflix Technology Blog</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Escrow Buddy: An open-source tool from Netflix for remediation of missing FileVault keys in MDM]]></title>
        <id>https://medium.com/p/815aef5107cd</id>
        <link href="https://netflixtechblog.com/escrow-buddy-an-open-source-tool-from-netflix-for-remediation-of-missing-filevault-keys-in-mdm-815aef5107cd?source=rss----2615bd06b42e---4"/>
        <updated>2023-06-12T16:36:25.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Netflix has open-sourced Escrow Buddy, which helps Security and IT teams ensure they have valid FileVault recovery keys for all their Macs…]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Netflix Technology Blog</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science and Technology links (June 11 2023)]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=20619</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2023/06/11/science-and-technology-links-june-11-2023/"/>
        <updated>2023-06-11T19:45:32.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Similar species can have vastly different lifespan. Researchers have been looking for the limiting factors that explain these differences. As we age, our genes are expressed differently through methylation. Different species vary their methylation at different speeds. There is some evidence that it could be that the methylation rate that determines the lifespan. If that … Continue reading Science and Technology links (June 11 2023)]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>