<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>urn:2024-05-19T00:59:39.959Z</id>
    <title>osmos::feed</title>
    <updated>2024-05-19T00:59:39.959Z</updated>
    <generator>osmosfeed 1.15.1</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="index.html"/>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning from the object-oriented mania]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21333</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/05/14/learning-from-the-object-oriented-mania/"/>
        <updated>2024-05-14T14:17:42.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back when I started programming professionally, every expert and every software engineering professor would swear by object-oriented programming. Resistance was futile. History had spoken: the future was object-oriented. It is hard to understate how strong the mania was. In education, we started calling textbooks and videos ‘learning objects‘. Educators would soon ‘combine learning objects and reuse them‘. A competitor … Continue reading Learning from the object-oriented mania]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Forwarding references in C++]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21331</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/05/13/forwarding-references-in-c/"/>
        <updated>2024-05-13T15:51:51.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[In C++, there are different ways to pass a value to a function. Typically, at any given time, an object in C++ ‘belongs’ to a single function. The various ways to call a function differ in who owns the object, the caller or the callee (the function being called). The simplest one is that we … Continue reading Forwarding references in C++]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peer review is not the gold standard in science]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21322</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/05/11/peer-review-is-not-the-gold-standard-in-science/"/>
        <updated>2024-05-11T22:47:16.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Peer review as we know it today was introduced very late, over a century after the scientific revolution. It happened after Einstein’s time… arguably the most productive era in science. Current scientists often equate a success with the publication in a selective peer-reviewed venue. But that was never the scientific paradigm. In fact, it is … Continue reading Peer review is not the gold standard in science]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How fast can you construct a small list of strings in C for Python?]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21316</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/05/09/how-fast-can-construct-small-list-of-strings-in-c-for-python/"/>
        <updated>2024-05-09T03:55:45.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Python is probably the most popular programming language in the world right now. Python is easy to extend using C code. You may want to return from Python a small data structure. When crossing from C to Python, there is an overhead. Thus, if performance is a concern, you do not want to return lots … Continue reading How fast can you construct a small list of strings in C for Python?]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Should Node.js be built with ClangCL under Windows?]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21309</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/05/02/should-node-js-be-built-with-clangcl-under-windows/"/>
        <updated>2024-05-02T19:23:11.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Under Windows, when using Visual Studio to build C++ code, there are two possible compiler strategies. The Visual Studio compiler (often referred to as MSVC) is the default compiler provided by Microsoft for Windows development. In Debug mode, the regular Visual Studio compiler produces faster compilation times and more performant code compared to ClangCL. ClangCL … Continue reading Should Node.js be built with ClangCL under Windows?]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brooklyn Botanical Garden]]></title>
        <id>https://thenumb.at/BBG/</id>
        <link href="https://thenumb.at/BBG/"/>
        <updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Brooklyn Botanical Garden, New York, NY, 2024]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Max Slater</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Careful with Pair-of-Registers instructions on Apple Silicon]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21297</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/04/29/careful-with-pair-of-registers-instructions-on-apple-silicon/"/>
        <updated>2024-04-29T00:32:38.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Egor Bogatov is an engineer working on C# compiler technology at Microsoft. He had an intriguing remark about a performance regression on Apple hardware following what appears to be an optimization. The .NET 9.0 runtime introduced the optimization where two loads (ldr) could be combined into a single load (ldp). It is a typical peephole … Continue reading Careful with Pair-of-Registers instructions on Apple Silicon]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Large language models (e.g., ChatGPT) as research assistants]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21288</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/04/27/large-language-models-e-g-chatgpt-as-research-assistants/"/>
        <updated>2024-04-27T00:05:24.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Software can beat human beings at most games… from Chess to Go, and even poker. Large language models like GPT-4 offered through services such as ChatGPT allow us to solve a new breed of problems. GPT-4 can beat 90% of human beings at the bar exam. Artificial intelligence can match math Olympians. The primary skills … Continue reading Large language models (e.g., ChatGPT) as research assistants]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How do you recognize an expert?]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21278</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/04/21/how-do-you-recognize-an-expert/"/>
        <updated>2024-04-21T17:35:28.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Go back to the roots: experience. An expert is someone who has repeatedly solved the concrete problem you are encountering. If your toilet leaks, an experienced plumber is an expert. An expert has a track record and has had to face the consequences of their work. Failing is part of what makes an expert: any … Continue reading How do you recognize an expert?]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[How quickly can you break a long string into lines?]]></title>
        <id>https://lemire.me/blog/?p=21272</id>
        <link href="https://lemire.me/blog/2024/04/19/how-quickly-can-you-break-a-long-string-into-lines/"/>
        <updated>2024-04-19T21:25:21.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Suppose that you receive a long string and you need to break it down into lines. Consider the simplified problems where you need to break the string into segments of (say) 72 characters. It is a relevant problem if your string is a base64 string or a Fortran formatted statement. The problem could be a … Continue reading How quickly can you break a long string into lines?]]></summary>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Lemire</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>